Bonnie Christensen Papers 2005.0088
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Bonnie Christensen Papers
undated, 1863-2006
2005.0088
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
15.7 Linear feet
The collection contains the original illustrations, woodcut blocks, research materials, and manuscript materials of Bonnie Christensen.
Christensen, Bonnie
Preferred Citation
[Item description, #:#] Bonnie Christensen Papers. Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the original illustrations, woodcut blocks, research materials, and manuscript materials of Bonnie Christensen.
Published Works
Ms. Christensen is a prolific author and illustrator. For a complete listing of her published works please visit her web site at http://bonniechristensen.com/ or check standard bibliographic resources such as WorldCat. Illustrator Citro, Joseph. Green Mountain Ghost Ghouls and Unsolved Mysteries, Houghton Mifflin Company, 1994. Thomas, Shelley M.. Putting the World to Sleep, Houghton Mifflin Company, 1995. Krensky, Stephen. Breaking into Print, Little Brown and Company, 1996. Steinbeck, John. The Grapes of Wrath, The Folio Society, 1998. Evan, Craig C.. Moon Over Tennessee, Houghton Mifflin Company, 1999. Moses, Sheila P.. I, Dred Scott, Margaret K. McElderry, 2005. Osborne, Mary P.. Pompeii, Lost and Found, Alfred A. Knopf, 2006. Nikola-Lisa, W.. Magic in the Margins, Houghton Mifflin Company, 2007. Myers, Walter D.. Ida B. Wells, Let the Truth Be Told, HarperCollins, 2008. Author and Illustrator An Edible Alphabet, Dial/Penguin, 1994. Rebus Riot, Dial/Penguin, 1997. Woody Guthrie: Poet of the People, Alfred A. Knopf, 2001. The Daring Nelly Bly: America's Star Reporter, Alfred A. Knopf, 2003. In My Grandmother's House, HarperCollins, 2003. Django, World's Greatest Jazz Guitarist, Roaring Brook Press, 2009.
Biography
Bonnie Christensen, born in 1951 in Saranac Lake, New York, is a children's book author and illustrator as well as an artist. Christensen earned a B.A. in Theatre and Communication from the University of Vermont. After college Christensen worked in New York theaters including Joe Papp's Public Theatre, New York Shakespeare Festival, Actor's Studio, Chelsea Theater, and Stella Adler Studio. In New York, Christensen became interested in playwriting while she worked for the Screen Actors Guild and then Paramount Pictures. While in New York, Christensen also studied wood engraving with John Depol and attended classes at Parsons School of Design and Center for Book Arts. Eventually, Christensen returned to Vermont and focused on wood engraving, exhibiting prints locally, and was offered her first illustration job. Through a keen interest in printmaking and letterpress printing Christensen eventually hand-printed and bound a limited- edition book. Desire to see that book reach a wider audience eventually led Christensen to trade publishers and initiated her career as an author and illustrator. Christensen began her career in children's literature in the mid-1990s, and since 2000 has worked to create children's books that highlight the lives of enigmatic Americans through self-illustrated picture books such as Woody Guthrie: Poet of the People and The Daring Nelly Bly: America's Star Reporter. Christensen and her books have recieved numerous awards including the Kirkus Reviews Best Children’s Books of 2006 award for Pompeii, Lost and Found, the Oppenheim Toy Portfolio Gold Award for The Daring Nellie Bly, the Parent’s Choice Gold Award 2002, the Horn Book-Boston Globe Honor Award 2002, and the ALA Notable Children’s Book 2002 award for Woody Guthrie, Poet of the People, and the International Reading Association Best Books of 2000 award for Moon Over Tennessee. In addition to her work as a children's book illustrator and author Christensen has also dedicated her time to teaching at St. Michael’s College in Burlington, VT, where she has been an adjunct professor of Fine Arts since 1995. As an artist Christensen's portfolio ranges from frescos and monotypes to woodengravings and etchings.
Provenance and Acquisition
This collection was donated by Bonnie Christensen on June 9, 2006.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Administrative Records.; Children's literature, American--20th century.; Children's literature--Manuscripts.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Northeast Children's Literature Collection.; Notes.; Photographs.; Realia.; Works of Art.
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1863-2002
  - Realia, correspondence, notes, prints, financial records, fliers, clippings, publications, photographs, 1863-1998 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    [Subjects include: woodblocks, Grapes of Wrath, printing history, Folio Society and Moon over Tennessee],
  - Photographs, prints, correspondence, notes, optical disks, clippings, manuscripts, books, fliers, periodicals, realia, 2000-2002 (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: Grandma’s photos, ‘final stories’, biography, stories submitted and comments, Grandmother Anthology, A Walk in the Woods, To Grandmother’s House, visual references, drawings, slave sale, unsigned author contracts, author lists and address’, ready to engrave prints, finals letters and contracts, drafts of letters and contracts, Moon over Tennessee sketches, Pa sleeps, Pa dies, Bodies after battle, The Road Home, Ma in doorway, Tennessee with moon over it, cards, tear sheets],
  - Notes, artwork, prints, photographs, books, undated, 1910, 1993 (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: Runs for Senate, Django, Apple, An Edible Alphabet, Bonnie’s schedule],
  - Artwork, prints, manuscripts, notes, fliers, clippings, 1994-2001 (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: Breaking into Print, Dial Books for Young Readers, The Folio Society, Houghton Mifflin, Children’s Books, Putting the World to Sleep, Bantam Doubleday Dell, Moon Over Tennessee, Nellie Bly, Return Jersey City, first map & second map, Mexico, New York, Blackwell’s Island, the Roosevelt Island Story, tailor],
  - Artwork, photographs, prints, manuscripts, clippings, notes, 1991-1993 (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: YAM, Xanthoriza, horseradish, zucchini, watermelon, vanilla, tomato, sunflower, raspberry, quince, pumpkin, oats, nasturtium, maple, lemon, kale, ipomea, juneberry, grape, hazelnut, eggplant, fig, dill, bluberry, corn, cover the dedication, text, colored copies, Rebus],
  - Manuscripts, notes, artwork, clippings, prints, correspondence, administrative records, postcards, publications, 1993, 1995 (Box 6)
    [Subjects include: Dummy, Illuminations, cut and pasted manuscripts, bread and water, completed jobs, Little Brown, stationary, multi-panel layouts, architecture, “Good Night World”, visual information, fine art paper, Grandma, historic roots],
  - Manuscripts, artwork, correspondence, undated (Box 7)
    [Subjects include: Rebus, Breaking into Print, Putting the world to sleep, Edible Alphabet],
  - Artwork, illustrations, 2006 (Box 8)
    Subjects include: assorted sketches, "British Scraper Board".
  - Realia, undated; 1.3 Linear feet (Box 9)
    Subjects include: Woodcuts for prints (in book).
  - Clippings, correspondence, illustrations, manuscripts, illustrations, photos, prints, undated; 1.3 Linear feet (Box 10)
    Subjects include: Miner Illustrations, Woody Gunthrie.
    General note
    Organization: folders.
  - Artwork, dummies, illustrations, manuscript, 1995; 1.3 Linear feet (Box 11)
    Subjects include: food, "Print: Before and After the Invention of the Press".
  - Artwork, illustration, posters, undated (Box 12)
    Subjects include: sketches for "Edible alphabet" and "Putting the world to sleep".
  - Dummies, galley proofs, illustrations (watercolor), maps, photographs (facsimilies & studies for illustrations), sketches (charcoal & ink), 1996, 2000 (Box 13)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects include: dummies and galley proofs for The Daring Nellie Bly, Woodie Guthrie, and Breaking Into Print (Johannes Gutenberg); America's Star Reporter.
  - Pencil sketches (5), storyboard (1)for Woody Guthrie, undated (Folder 14)